<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><title>Analytics Drive - Education</title><link href="https://analyticsdrive.tech/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://analyticsdrive.tech/feeds/education.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://analyticsdrive.tech/</id><updated>2026-02-16T21:50:00+00:00</updated><entry><title>JEE Main 2026 Session 1 Results Declared</title><link href="https://analyticsdrive.tech/jee-main-2026-session-1-results-declared/" rel="alternate"/><published>2026-02-16T21:50:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-02-16T21:50:00+00:00</updated><author><name>Admin</name></author><id>tag:analyticsdrive.tech,2026-02-16:/jee-main-2026-session-1-results-declared/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The wait is over! NTA has declared JEE Main 2026 Session 1 results. Find out how to check your scorecard, understand your percentile, and plan your next steps.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="jee-main-2026-session-1-results-declared-your-gateway-to-engineering-dreams"&gt;JEE Main 2026 Session 1 Results Declared: Your Gateway to Engineering Dreams!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The moment lakhs of engineering aspirants across the nation have been eagerly awaiting is finally here! The National Testing Agency (NTA) has officially released the JEE Main 2026 Session 1 results today, February 16, 2026. This announcement marks a significant milestone for students who appeared for the examination held from January 21 to 29, 2026. If you've been on the edge of your seat, it's time to check your scores and plan your future!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog post will guide you through checking your results, understanding your scorecard, deciphering the NTA percentile, and outlining the crucial next steps, whether you're aiming for JEE Advanced, NITs, IIITs, or exploring other exciting avenues.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="how-to-check-your-jee-main-2026-session-1-result"&gt;How to Check Your JEE Main 2026 Session 1 Result&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Checking your JEE Main 2026 Session 1 scorecard is a straightforward process. Follow these steps to access your results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visit the Official NTA JEE Website:&lt;/strong&gt; Head over to jeemain.nta.nic.in.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Locate the Result Link:&lt;/strong&gt; On the homepage, look for the link that reads "JEE Main 2026 Session 1 Result" or "View Score Card".&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enter Your Credentials:&lt;/strong&gt; You will be redirected to a new page where you need to enter your Application Number and Date of Birth (or password).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complete CAPTCHA:&lt;/strong&gt; Enter the security pin or CAPTCHA code as displayed on the screen.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Submit:&lt;/strong&gt; Click on the "Submit" button.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Download Your Scorecard:&lt;/strong&gt; Your JEE Main 2026 Session 1 scorecard will appear on the screen. Download it as a PDF and take a printout for future reference.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember, the result is available online only; there is no offline or postal distribution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="understanding-your-jee-main-scorecard-and-percentile"&gt;Understanding Your JEE Main Scorecard and Percentile&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Your JEE Main 2026 Session 1 scorecard is more than just a piece of paper; it's a detailed report of your performance. Here's what you'll find on it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Candidate's Details:&lt;/strong&gt; Your name, application number, roll number, date of birth, category, and state of eligibility.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Subject-wise NTA Scores:&lt;/strong&gt; Your normalized scores for Physics, Chemistry, and Mathematics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Total NTA Score (Percentile):&lt;/strong&gt; This is your overall percentile score.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's important to note that the scorecard will display your NTA scores, which are not the same as raw marks or percentages. The NTA score is a normalized score, reflecting your relative performance compared to all other candidates who appeared in the same session, ensuring fairness across multiple shifts with varying difficulty levels. A higher percentile indicates that you performed better than that percentage of candidates in your session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The official cut-off and All India Rank (AIR) will not be mentioned on this scorecard. The final AIR will be declared after Session 2 results are out, considering the best percentile from both sessions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="whats-next-after-jee-main-2026-session-1-results"&gt;What's Next After JEE Main 2026 Session 1 Results?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Receiving your JEE Main Session 1 result opens up several pathways. Here’s a breakdown of your potential next steps:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="option-1-aiming-for-jee-advanced-and-iits"&gt;Option 1: Aiming for JEE Advanced and IITs&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've scored well and are among the top 2,50,000 successful candidates (including all categories) in the B.E./B.Tech paper of JEE Main 2026, you are eligible to register and appear for JEE Advanced 2026. Qualifying JEE Advanced is the gateway to admissions in the prestigious Indian Institutes of Technology (IITs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remember the key eligibility criteria for JEE Advanced 2026:
*   You must be among the top 2,50,000 JEE Main qualifiers.
*   You should have been born on or after October 1, 2001 (with age relaxation for SC/ST/PwD candidates).
*   You can attempt JEE Advanced a maximum of two times in two consecutive years.
*   You must have appeared for your Class XII (or equivalent) examination for the first time in either 2025 or 2026 with Physics, Chemistry, and Mathematics as compulsory subjects.
*   You must also meet the Class 12th board percentage criteria, which is typically 75% aggregate (65% for SC/ST/PwD) or be in the top 20 percentile of your respective board.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Start preparing immediately if JEE Advanced is your goal!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="option-2-appearing-for-jee-main-session-2"&gt;Option 2: Appearing for JEE Main Session 2&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not satisfied with your Session 1 score? Don't worry, the NTA provides another opportunity. You can appear for JEE Main Session 2 to improve your score. The best percentile from both sessions will be considered for your final All India Rank (AIR). Many students opt for Session 2 to better their performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="option-3-admissions-to-nits-iiits-gftis-and-other-colleges"&gt;Option 3: Admissions to NITs, IIITs, GFTIs, and Other Colleges&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless of whether you appear for JEE Advanced, your JEE Main score is crucial for admissions to National Institutes of Technology (NITs), Indian Institutes of Information Technology (IIITs), and Government-funded Technology Institutes (GFTIs).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Joint Seat Allocation Authority (JoSAA) will conduct counseling for admissions to these institutes based on JEE Main ranks, including IITs for those who qualify JEE Advanced. If your score doesn't qualify you for the top-tier institutions, many private engineering colleges also accept JEE Main scores. It's wise to research institutions and their cut-offs, and have a backup plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="option-4-exploring-alternative-career-paths"&gt;Option 4: Exploring Alternative Career Paths&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If engineering is not your only interest, or if your results don't align with your initial expectations, remember that numerous other promising career paths are available. Fields like science, research, management, design, and government services offer dynamic and fulfilling careers. Evaluate your score, research various options, and make informed decisions aligned with your long-term goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="congratulations-and-good-luck"&gt;Congratulations and Good Luck!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A heartfelt congratulations to all students who appeared for JEE Main 2026 Session 1! Whether you achieved your desired score or are looking for ways to improve, remember that this is just one step in your academic journey. Evaluate your performance, understand your options, and approach the next phase with renewed determination. Good luck with your future endeavors!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="further-reading-resources"&gt;Further Reading &amp;amp; Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;National Testing Agency (NTA) Official Website:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://nta.ac.in/"&gt;https://nta.ac.in/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JEE Main Official Website:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://jeemain.nta.nic.in/"&gt;https://jeemain.nta.nic.in/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;JEE Advanced Official Website:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://jeeadv.ac.in/"&gt;https://jeeadv.ac.in/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Joint Seat Allocation Authority (JoSAA) Official Website:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;a href="https://josaa.nic.in/"&gt;https://josaa.nic.in/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content><category term="Education"/><category term="JEE Main"/><category term="NTA Result"/><category term="Engineering Entrance"/><category term="JEE 2026"/><category term="Career Advice"/><media:content height="675" medium="image" type="image/webp" url="https://analyticsdrive.tech/images/jee-main-2026-session-1-results-declared.webp" width="1200"/><media:title type="plain">JEE Main 2026 Session 1 Results Declared</media:title><media:description type="plain">The wait is over! NTA has declared JEE Main 2026 Session 1 results. Find out how to check your scorecard, understand your percentile, and plan your next steps.</media:description></entry></feed>